George Peck Papers
George Peck Papers
1793-1878
Peck, George,1797-1876.
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American Methodist Episcopal clergyman, author, and President of Cazenovia Seminary, a Methodist-supported school in Madison County, New York. Collection includes correspondence (1793-1878); financial records (1823-1876); an autbiographical essay; diaries (1852-1875); notebooks (1856-1868); sermons; and personal memorabilia, including clippings, financial records, and photographs.
149466
Biographical History
George Peck (1797-1876) was an American Methodist Episcopal clergyman, author, and President of Cazenovia Seminary, a Methodist-supported school in Madison County, New York. Through his daughter Mary, he is the grandfather of American novelist and poet Stephen Crane.
Born on August 8, 1797 in Middlefield, New York, Peck was associated with the Methodist Episcopal Church throughout his life. He married Mary Myers on June 10, 1819 and the couple had five children: George Myers, Luther W., Mary, William Fletcher (died aged 7 months), and Wilbur Frank. Peck received his A.M. degree from Wesleyan University in 1835 and a D.D. from August College in 1840. He became president of Cazenovia Seminary in 1835, and was also the editor of the Methodist Quarterly Review and the New York Advocate. He died in Scranton, Pennsylvania on May 20, 1876.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Peck Papers consists of correspondence, financial material, memorabilia, miscellanea, published material, and writings.
Correspondence (1793-1878) includes personal, financial and business letters. Financial material (1823-1876) consists mainly of receipts. Memorabilia contains such articles as eyeglasses and a stereoscope card of Peck Hall. Published material consists of advertisements, clippings, and copies of Methodist Quarterly Review and The Ladies' Repository. Writings includes a set of diaries from 1852-1875, as well as articles, sermons and reports pertaining to the Methodist Episcopal Church for which Peck worked.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and financial material are arranged chronologically. Memorabilia, published material, anmd writings are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
has extensive holdings related to Methodist church and clergy. For a complete listing of manuscript collections please refer to. For a complete listed of published material (monographs, periodicals, broadsides, etc.) please refer to.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Peck, George, 1797-1876.; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Clergy.; Clergy -- United States.; Clergy as authors.; Educators -- United States.; Methodists -- United States.; Autobiographies (literary works); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Financial records.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Sermons.; Authors.; Clergy.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1793-1798 (Box 1)
  - 1803 (Box 1)
  - 1819-1859, 39 folders (Box 1)
  - 1860-1878, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)
- Financial papers
  - 1823-1876, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Bookplates (Box 2)
  - Business cards (Box 2)
  - Deed (Box 2)
  - Eyeglasses (Box 2)
  - Golden wedding anniversary poem and program, 1869 (Box 2)
  - Leather pouch (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Peck family genealogy (Box 2)
  - Penwiper (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Print of George Peck (Oversize 1)
  - Railroad certificate (Box 2)
  - Seeds (Box 2)
  - Stereoscope card of Peck Hall (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - 1852-1858 (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Advertising materials (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1838-1871 (Box 3)
  - Evangelical Alliance, 1846 (Box 3)
  - The Ladies' Repository, Jul 1843; Jun 1859,; Apr 1860,; Oct 1864 (Box 3)
  - Map of camp meeting ground, 1869 (Box 3)
  - Methodist Quarterly Review, Apr 1862; Jul 1880 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1853-1875 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets, 1832-1872 (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Autobiographical sketch, 1813 (Box 3)
  - Autobiography (Box 3)
  - Bank book, 1863-1868 (Box 3)
  - Camp meetings, 1870 (Box 3)
  - Camp accounts book, 1821-1826 (Box 3)
  - Cash book, 1837-1838 (Box 3)
  - Cash book, 1870-1871 (Box 3)
  - Catholicity, 1866 (Box 3)
  - Diaries
    - 1852-1863, missing 1857 and 1860, 10 volumes (Box 4)
    - 1863, 1867, 1868, 1870, 1872, 1873, 1875, 7 volumes (Box 4)
  - Family record (Box 4)
  - Farm book, 1867-1868 (Box 4)
  - First Methodist Class at Ross Hill (Box 4)
  - History of Sanford Charge (Box 4)
    A transcript of this document is available in the finding aids files.
  - History of the Sheshequin Charge, 1868 (Box 4)
  - Journal, 1846 (Box 4)
  - Memorandums of circuit travels, 1816-1818 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1821-1861 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous notebooks, 1856-1865; 3 volumes (Box 5)
  - Notebook, 1868 (Box 5)
  - Report of the Committee on Pastoral Address (Box 5)
  - The Seminary As It Relates to the Ministry (Box 5)
  - Sermon notes, 1820-1834, 1849-1860; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Sermons and speeches
    - National evils and their remedy, 1841 (Box 5)
    - The past and the present, 1866 (Box 5)
  - Subscription book, 1857 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming Camp Meeting Association stock record (Box 5)
  - Wyoming District Meeting records, 1871-1873 (Box 5)